so we have two goals in the evening
classes one is to again to teach the ACI
courses there are 36 courses 33 if you
don't count the review courses we're
hoping to do three courses a year to do
them over again I haven't taught them in
27 years okay so I started them 27 years
ago and we recorded them with my dog
barking in the house and so we're trying
to kind of do it over again probably
there's things in the early recordings
that you should listen to when you have
time because I had a you know I was in
the middle of the Geshe course at that
point I think this time through will be
more kind of a friendly presentation of
it of someone who's been teaching for 40
years and talking to people who who want
to be teachers and I think you may I'm a
mix in a lot of advices on how to teach
and and new ideas I've had about the
courses since I first wrote them but I
would say reading them over recently to
prepare for this course they're good
they're good stuff and they stand
I have never to my memory I've never had
a correction from someone a substantial
correction for the for the courses they
there are good translations they are the
real thing none of it is my writing a
hundred percent of the courses except
for one page which is secret so I think
it's 6,000 pages of translation and it's
all straight translation none of its by
me so it's all the great classics of
ancient times and I think it was the
first time and I think Jeff will
appreciate it that we were able to put
in the original language we
the translation so every paragraph has
the original sutras and scriptures in
the six thousand pages so if you know if
anyone thinks something is wrong or a
mistaken or gets a lot put his own ideas
in it you can actually check the Tibetan
or the Sanskrit and you can see every
single word where it came from so I
think and in that sense the courses are
amazing and we're gonna the kind of the
what we'll be doing in the evening is
we'll go through the course material
yeah for each class so there are ten
classes in course one and I'll go
through the material for each class you
will do the normal homeworks for the ACI
courses so even if you've done them
before I don't care there was a
punishment in the monastery for young
monks who snuck off across the corn
fields it's about a two hour walk to the
local town to see movies and if you get
caught you have to hold an Indian movie
poster up in the assembly for two hours
you can't put it down or you get
massaged and and then you have to do
prostrations you have to do like a
thousand frustrations to all the monks
and there was a big argument in the
monastery that this was not a punishment
this was an honor and so doing the
homeworks again it's an honor and it'll
increase your understanding so I don't
care if you've done them before you're
gonna do them again all right and please
turn your homeworks in on time which
leads me to another thing I'm 27 years
older than I was before and I'm too old
to deal with bad behavior and people who
don't turn in their assignments and you
know I'm not a babysitter any more than
when I first did the courses I was a
babysitter
and I I lost a lot of hair by doing the
babysitting and and I'm assuming you are
all mature you know stable people that I
want you to behave well while you're
here and I expect you to and I frankly
I'm too old to put up with any
misbehavior it's usually three people
who take half the staffs time and I'm
not gonna we're not gonna do it okay if
you don't want to do your homeworks on
time or you can't get her on time or you
have some other personal problems then
go solve them come back to the next one
okay and I'm just gonna be a tough guy
yeah right okay so I'm gonna go through
you've got two homeworks you're gonna be
doing one is the ACI course homework and
then secondly you'll be doing a separate
homework for the teacher training which
will include tips about how to teach
what's the purpose of the agent classic
Institute you know how did we come up
with it what's the structure things like
that okay so you'll have two homeworks
to do every day and we left you a block
of time unlike the SC I am classes when
you have what you have to do at midnight
we late we gave you two hours I think
Tim am i right two hours in the
afternoon to do your homeworks okay so
there's no excuse I wrote it in 20
minutes so you can do it in two hours
okay
so I'm gonna go straight to the homework
because I have a bad habit of forgetting
to go through the homework and just
talking about stories and I'm gonna make
sure I go through the two homeworks with
you okay probably in well I'll probably
just mix it up okay teacher training
stuff and now let's do the teacher
training stuff first and then I'll do
the coursework okay so here we go
general comments and I'm gonna be
following your homework so maybe your
first homework question
what is the mission of the Asian
classics Institute
what is a CIA meant to do what are we
supposed to be doing why why why are you
becoming a teacher and what's the
purpose of the organization of a CRE
okay so first of all a sea-ice mission
is to we call it accuracy relevance the
accurate relevant and accessible okay
those are three words I expect on your
homework accurate relevant and
accessible we want to bring the ancient
wisdom of Buddhism 25 centuries
two-and-a-half thousand years to the
modern world in a way which is accurate
relevant and accessible okay so what do
I mean by these three things accurate
means the stuff is good stuff I almost
said a bad word it's good stuff okay
it's the real Buddhism it's all the
ancient texts and Jing and it it's
really really translated correctly and
it's all there the original is in the
document so there's even people who have
spent part of their lives hyper texting
connecting the English to the Tibetan
just to make dictionaries so there's
there's been teams for the last 20 years
just connecting the words to and they've
confirmed that all the words are there
okay so it's accurate okay and and when
you pass it on you're gonna do it
accurately okay and you're gonna pass it
down correctly okay this stuff is there
it's like a recipe for a cake okay like
it's a really tasty cake and our hostel
gave me his Guadalajara enchilada brown
sauce what's this Chile's called the
poblano yeah I use Anaheim's you use pop
um but uh he has a recipe for a Mexican
dish right
it's his mom's there's some like that
like it was very kind of him to give it
to me it's highly secret and I made him
for Veronica and she loves him so anyway
but you don't mess with the recipe
okay the recipe has worked for 25
centuries okay
it has worked for the world for $0.25
races so don't mess with it
and we believe okay check this out we
believe that the person who started the
tradition was omniscient our mission is
not like your mom who doesn't know
exactly where you were keeping stuff in
your room although she knew you very
well omniscient means they can see
everything about you about your life
they can read your mind they know every
detail of your life the person who wrote
the original materials is watching this
class right now 25 centuries ago okay so
don't think you're gonna improve on what
they did okay
don't think they left something out or
they didn't know that I don't know
bubblegum was gonna be popular they know
everything okay
so trust it okay don't mess with it all
right that's my first thing
it was incredible amount of work to
translate 6,000 pages don't mess it up
okay if you want to teach you know when
you call it psychic healing or something
do it on your own time okay do it don't
do it in an ACI class you're free as an
ACI teacher we don't require that you
follow Buddhism you don't have to be a
Buddhist to teach a tre okay and there
are many people around the world you
know who are not Buddhist who come to
ACI and especially DCI courses I don't
care what you are 99% of the people in
the world follow what their parents did
and
fine I had a guy in Ireland you guys
know him
Kevin Thornton from Galway and he says
giggle I like this stuff you know but my
daughters getting married in is it okay
she may get married in the Galloway
Cathedral and not in our basement with
the 12 arm the other locket is about is
this okay cuz it's more comfortable for
everyone you know so yeah whatever your
parents did whatever church synagogue
mosque you went to as a kid make your
parents happy make your family
comfortable do the holidays you know I
don't do Hanukkah I do Christmas
I still like Christmas these are
cultural things you know whatever you
did Spring Festival I don't know as a
kid with your parents keep peace in your
family okay
I'm we're not trying to make you fanatic
okay we're trying to spread information
that can help everybody in the world and
it does not have to be connected to a
religion okay and if you choose to be a
Buddhist or you want to become a nun
like some wonderful people here that's
fine you know become a nun teach a CI
that's fine okay but you don't have to
okay it's up to you okay do whatever is
legal in your country that's fine okay
and you don't have to look like a guru
or a Lama or a priest we are not making
gurus we are not making Lamas we are not
making priests we're just offering
information to people which will help
them with their lives and and in a CI
with their future lives and all their
lives to come and it will not help just
people who attend a business seminar it
will help the entire universe and
there's a time in your practice in your
meditations when you will meet the
universe and every being in the universe
if you play your cards right they say in
English if you study well
and you keep to the program and you do
your meditations and your practices you
can personally meet every living being
in this universe and and get to know
them and love them okay the human mind
has this capacity do the emptiness okay
so you know think be okay the purpose of
a CI is to help the whole world it's not
a Buddhist sect or a small Buddhist
thing okay
it's a it's a way of acting and thinking
and practicing that can help anyone so
we're not forcing people to follow a
certain religion or something like okay
it's it doesn't matter what your parents
had on your altar at home do that okay
that's fine have a crucifix in your I
have you know and that's fine and I I
feel happy with it okay keep the
holidays of your own culture your own
country okay add to the spice of life
this delicious ice cream called ACI okay
and make your life more beautiful and
whole okay
and we're not here to convince people or
make them join something or there's no
leader okay
there's a bald guy in the desert you
know teaching yeah later it'll be
somebody else it'll be you guys okay
you'll be bald too I'm Tanya and that's
how you know when you're wise so I told
him his hair cut it he's cut the size
but for me it would work the other way
so me and John okay so I think one of
the most important things I'd say about
the ACI courses is have fun don't be a
fanatic okay
don't be a fundamentalist you know have
fun life is incredibly short yesterday I
was 25 I swear to God I was 25 yesterday
I swear and then blue and I'm 66 and I
wore what happened you know
don't get too serious about your life
okay don't be like grumpy and you know
like this you know life goes like that
you might as well have fun a CI should
be fun I don't want like people being
when you call it you have to do it this
way or you're a bad person
you know come on we're all gonna die
mother we're in a boat that's sinking in
the middle of the Pacific let's play
some music and eat a lot before it goes
down have fun teaching a thank you okay
nobody likes that grumpy ACI teacher or
stressed out I was in the back of a
meditation class I went to spy on one of
our new teachers many years ago they're
not here anymore don't worry bud and two
ladies were sitting in front of me and I
snuck in in the back and I sent behind
these two ladies and the teacher was
like really nervous and drinking tea
like this and all upset and angry and
uptight you know like you got to do it
like you know and then this one lady
turned to the other lady and she said uh
what do you think I don't know you know
I don't know what kind of meditation
she's teaching but whatever it is I
don't want to learn it cuz I don't want
to be like that okay so be happy have
fun the minute you become a teacher
you're gonna get extra trouble because
the demons don't like it okay so trust
me
starting tonight you're gonna have more
trouble more problems more difficult
people going to show up and just tell
them the demons to you and have fun okay
Cass what are you gonna do with your
life you know you're gonna be grumpy
your whole life you're gonna tell people
what to do okay
so keep it but keep it accurate okay
number one accurate okay number two
relevant
okay like tie these courses to people's
real life okay
never teach a class without tying the
ancient wisdom to people's real problems
real life okay like you're not teaching
some ancient books you're teaching
people how to be happy okay if you're a
success people will be happy I got a
photo from Jeffrey it saw in Taiwan
yesterday and he went to DC i2 which is
how to find your talent or your passion
in life he went to a group of 50 blind
people and taught them these the eye -
okay and then they all said I want to be
this I want to be this this one young
lady stood up and said I want to be a
competitive Archer ancient archery
ancient Chinese archery you know this is
in Taiwan right she was to be a Archer
she's blind
you know and he's like okay let's do it
let's plant the seeds you know and he
sent me a photo yesterday she's in a
Karcher II competition now and she
almost hit the middle and they agreed
that it was okay to put a bell in the
middle of the target so she just listens
for the bell and she shoots at the Bell
so don't wear bells to those
competitions but it was so cool and they
have such fun you know the group is just
I met some of them came to my yoga class
meet me and Alex taught them from
Colorado it's a country north of here
and it was so much fun you know and we
just had fun so look you have problems I
have problems okay we all have problems
as a teacher you're gonna multiply your
problems okay and but just realize other
people have worse problems okay we're
not blind
okay and we don't have cancer we're
still walking and
we have a brain and we can study these
beautiful things okay so be a little
happy okay okay so relevant to people's
lives
second role what's the first rule again
accurate don't mess with the recipe
right it's not gonna taste this name and
it won't work the same okay I call it
selling fire extinguishers that don't
work and I can't think of anything more
cynical or mean than to try to make
extra money by selling a fire
extinguisher that doesn't work and you
know it doesn't work okay so if you want
to mess with this fire extinguisher this
fire extinguisher is called a CI courses
36 courses okay it works you you get a
fire you push the button the fire goes
out if your husband's mean to you or
your boss is being his usual self any
problem you have you push this ACI
course a fire extinguisher it will put
out the fire and and the fire called
death okay
it puts it out but if you mess with it
and it doesn't work anymore can you
imagine people like oh my mom's time
what do I do
oh just shoot him with a CI six yeah
well I changed it it doesn't work
anymore okay understand it's it's big
important stakes it's an important thing
okay it's like the only recipe for aids
to treat AIDS like the only formula in
the world don't mess with it
okay you can save millions of lives but
don't say oh this this needs a little
sugar in it yeah okay and then it
doesn't work for the people who have
AIDS okay all right so that's the
mission oh did I say what was the last
one
accessible okay don't there's a big
temptation for baby teachers and baby
yoga teachers to show off how much they
know
and do poses that nobody else in the
room can do and then you're not teaching
anymore you're just showing off you see
really you want to think about the poses
that are going to help the people in the
class you know they don't care if you
can do it some weird pose they just want
to be healthy okay so make it accessible
you can use Sanskrit words Chinese words
Pali you can show off sometimes okay I
allow it I maybe do it sometimes but
it's not the point okay it we want the
information to be open to everybody we
want it's a CI courses are open source
okay anyone can download an ACI course
they've been online for 19 years 20
years okay and they're free and they're
online anyone can download them we lost
count after the second year of the
number of downloads it was up to 150
thousand ten okay multiply that times
ten or more I don't know okay so we
wanted people to use it okay don't be
stingy and don't be weird you know
don't use weird words and things that
people can't understand judge your
audience
stay with the level of your audience if
it means you have to throw out your
lesson plan for the day do it in two
seconds okay stay with the level of your
audience okay make it accessible okay if
the audience wants you to go deeper like
if they're from a certain country I know
then then accessible means deeper go
deeper okay but watch your audience stay
with your audience and go deeper if you
need and but always accessible and
interesting and fun okay if it's boring
it's not accessible okay if it's dry
it's not accessible if you're not
prepared
to teach the class it's not accessible
okay and by the way people are like dogs
okay the dog you hear barking on the AC
I won recordings okay whose name was
Pancho via because he was from Mexico he
was a Chihuahua and a mean to all but uh
you know I had some students I had I
started a CI with six students okay they
came to my kitchen and we sat around the
kitchen and John still oh this weird guy
said let's record everything and I'm
like why what's the point
sorry okay
and people would come in to go to class
you know and I remember this one lady
who didn't like dogs and she opened the
door she stepped in and he ran up and
gone and bitterling and oh my god we had
to go to the hospital she was gonna sue
me I will talk about that kind of stuff
later and the thing is before she said
anything and before she did anything the
dog could tell she didn't like dogs they
have some ESP or some dog clairvoyance
okay and they can tell and your students
and a CI can tell if you're prepared or
not okay
you can't be us you can't fake it okay
you don't know in five minutes whether
you know your stuff or not so just cover
yourself know your stuff know your
material okay don't think that students
don't know the students know everything
about you they know your bad habits they
know you didn't meditate yesterday they
can smell it okay so the safest thing is
to be a good person and don't have any
secret you seen I mean be prepared for
your class okay cool
all right and it takes preparation cuz
this is real stuff
okay this is hard stuff and it takes
preparation and you will be so much
happier if you spend make time to spend
a few hours to get ready okay for your
classes
alright so the mission is to present by
the way this is a homework question the
mission and is to present this ancient
wisdom openly to the world without any
need for them to join anything or become
a certain sect or something okay and
it's accurate and it applies to their
real life and they can it's accessible
to everybody it's meant to be accessible
okay and the the immediate goal okay go
stop sushi a famous concept in Buddhism
what's the immediate goal is they learn
the material okay
the immediate goal for this week is you
guys learn the classic bites at
tsongkhapa called the three principal
paths right of Buddhism principle
teaches Buddhism okay that's the
immediate goal we call what's it called
Gooper okay good good so sushi is the
immediate goal the next goal is to make
people's lives
happier okay make their life happier
life is hard everyone has to die
we all get stick you lose you're gonna
lose every person you ever met and
you're gonna lose everything you ever
collected on the way money houses family
you're gonna lose everything okay so the
short term goal is to give people some
happiness okay make them happy another
goal of a CI and especially DCI is to
change
the way the world works okay right now
for example economically politically the
model is competition I will sell more
stuff than you coca-cola fights Pepsi
Cola Conda G fights McDonald's who can
make the most money okay this is and a
lot of this thinking comes from America
I'm sorry if I faster stronger harder
fight with the other guys I can I can
make more money I can be I can get more
things okay
ACI teaches the opposite is true and
thinking that you get more by being
faster stronger meaner is a very serious
mistake that causes all the conflict in
the world personal conflict company
conflict international conflict war
comes from this thinking that if you
fight for more you can get it okay so a
CIA mission immediate mission make
people happier in their home life in
their work life second mission change
the model of the world okay if it's true
that I will make more money by helping
others to make money if it's true that
America will have more energy supplies
if they supply more oil to China for
example if that's true then as an ACI
teacher you can change the model that
the whole world is working by and would
that be cool you know would that be cool
that would be something cool and my
dream is that as anonymous people don't
remember the name of the guy who started
ACI and they don't even remember that it
was a CI who got the new model started
maybe a CI can go away by then it's just
the model and when kids want something
their parents teach him to give it to
someone else and that becomes the model
of the whole world so the next goal the
second goal
of a CI first goal make people happy and
give them some comfort in this difficult
life okay second goal change the model
of the world in a quiet way and maybe we
never get credit and that's a fine
that's the credit okay third goal okay
don't be a frog in a well there's many
many worlds that you have not seen okay
don't don't think your little world is
the end of all things okay
I mean a woman came from Asia China to
diem a couple years ago a couple years
ago and she went outside at night and
saw the stars okay she's from Shanghai
okay the stars never shine in Shanghai
rarely and and she looked up you know
and she's like there were millions
billions of stars this is the best place
to see stars one of the best places in
the world to see stars we're two hours
from the nearest serious grocery store
okay and and she came in and she asked
the director to sinner I are they gonna
be here tomorrow I was gonna be here
tomorrow you know so all you have to do
to understand the far goal of a CI is to
go out tonight
and look at this guy if it's if the by
the way it's gonna get hot now it's
starting tomorrow so you're gonna be
complaining about the heat so enjoy the
the spring Arizona spring is one day
and it goes through and I can enjoy it
cuz you're gonna be complaining about
the air conditioning tomorrow bring warm
clothes to class if you're from
countries that don't grow up on the air
conditioner like we do okay so bring
like Luca you know bring a nice heavy
coat tickle don't get sick but many
people have gotten sick here from the
air conditioner okay bring a scarf head
coat okay because I keep the room cold
and you're gonna learn to keep the room
called because otherwise people fall
asleep if they're freezing they can't
fall asleep they get sick but okay
that's after you leave okay so go out
and look at the Stars and that's where
we're headed you know my next planet is
Sirius Star System follow the two feet
of Orion it's the bright blue star off
to his left foot and so don't think
smile okay there's just look up don't
think this is the only world
don't be come on you know the world's a
little bigger than that okay and it's
fully the intention and goal of ACI to
spread this on other planets okay
in other worlds there are many worlds in
this room that you can't see there are
many kinds of beings in this room you
can't see okay and we're not stopping
with this world we're not stopping with
changing the paradigm the model of this
world because there are other worlds
that are suffering also you will see
them in time right now you're not so
worried about it you know oh that's in
another country that's in Africa I don't
need to worry about it you know yeah but
there's other worlds that we have to
take care of okay so the goal is kind of
is not less than destroying death in all
worlds okay and you have the capacity to
do that each person in this room
how's the capacity to do that okay don't
think small okay don't think small
your goal is bigger okay I go this
bigger ACI scores is that and you one
day you will see it okay and you'll say
Oh guess I was right for once okay I put
a second question here it says what's
not the mission of a CI I don't know you
could say a lot of things I don't want
to be unfriendly I don't want to be a
cult I don't want to be a certain
religion I don't want to be mean to
people and say you're not my religion
you know I don't want us to be famous so
far we've been really good you know
combined a senior detail is the largest
Buddhist based organization in the world
but we don't talk about it okay I don't
care it doesn't matter you know it's not
we're not here as teachers to get
people's attention now every person in
this room likes people's attention
including the one talking but you got to
deal with it okay and as a teacher you
have to chip chip control yourself a
little bit okay we're not here to make
gurus Lamas Imams priests ministers
pastors you know kung fu masters it's
not the goal okay we're here as servants
to share what we had the good fortune to
learn from our teachers and it's not
about you or me okay it's about helping
people okay all right so that's what
we're not we're not here for a
personality cult and we're not here to
make any Michael king of the world
or anybody else okay we're here to help
people okay all right second question on
your homework
what kinds of people teach the formal
ACI courses who can teach ACI I think
it's an important question to start with
now we have an esteemed group of
professors for this
course they are very very senior as
senior as me right JB and they are
kick-ass practitioners JB has been
meditating on or forty years he he and
Connie both finished three-year retreats
jing-mei has finished very long retreats
they've been in the business for a long
time they're good at it okay
the teachers are very good at it and we
have a plan to develop the course with
you to collaborate with you it's
something we stole from Stanley an
elephant you know let the students
design the course and I can relax and
eat chili rellenos more often okay so
our dream is that we work with you and
we work with each other so the
professor's will be meeting every
lunchtime after our yoga practice which
everyone's gonna do someone was timing
today how much their body hurts and why
they can't do yoga and I'm like duh but
uh come and sit on the mat and do
something you know
it's okay you don't have to do
everything that everybody else does
forget everybody else do some stretching
let the body get blood you know be
healthier okay after yoga we will have a
our lunch with the professors but we
want your feedback how to make this a
cool course and how to teach it more
effectively okay you're the first
experiment you're the laboratory but we
want the laboratory rats to tell us what
they like what they don't like how they
think they could we can improve the
teacher training so we're kind of
keeping it fluid what we realized
already is that you cannot teach a
teacher for a week and let them go
that would be like training a heart
surgeon in a week and giving them a
razor blade and saying go for it okay so
we kind of made a decision which is
negotiate a table okay because you're
all helping us develop it this course we
think come to three courses and then we
talk about certifying you for the first
one okay got it and you don't have to do
them in order if you're from South
Africa welcome there's been an
underground ACI group in South Africa
for a hundred years we finally met after
I don't know 20 years but you know you
you can you're welcome
to help design the course help us design
the course and I think it's gonna take
three courses to really give you enough
foundation to give you a razorblade ends
to go say do heart operations okay
and they don't have to be in order well
see if you're from South Africa come
come next year and the year after
now the answer to the question geshe-la
try to talk about the questions okay is
that anyone can teach ACI anyone
the courses are free online the
materials are free online we locked them
you can't change them unless you retype
them or something okay anyone is welcome
to teach what we call living room
courses okay
and ideally less than 15 people in a
living room and you came to one class at
a CI you can you're very welcome
to share it with your friends okay
there's no limits on the materials you
can use the materials you can you're
welcome to share with friends I expect
you to teach at least one ACI course one
class on the airplane on the way home to
the person sitting next to you okay and
that you don't have to come to three
courses to have permission to do that
okay everyone in the world has
permission to sit down with their
friends in their living room I know the
Guadalajara skyscraper penthouse karma
they have this karma to have the most
beautiful flooring in the city what's
given to them to dip for their classes
with a swimming pool on it at the top of
the building and the bar they don't go
to okay and so you're welcome to sit in
your living room and and teach friends
okay
if your country does not allow religious
teaching even in a living room you're
still welcome to take this training and
we ask you to teach it outside of your
country okay if your country doesn't
allow these kinds of teaching in that
country we require that you go to
another location if you want to teach
okay
and if I find out that people who are in
a country where it's not allowed are
endangering themselves or other people I
will remove your certification okay so
clear
all right and it's possible well in
English they say where there's a will
there's a way if you love people enough
you will find a way to do it legally and
correctly okay
and I don't want anyone getting in
trouble all right okay so that's what
kinds of people can teach ACI the answer
is anybody if you have a head even
without a head if you can find a way to
express yourself okay
certified teacher has to come to the
training certified teacher who's listed
on the website as a certified teacher
you we have to train you okay you have
to go through the training okay how many
classes you have to come how many course
you have to come here how much can you
do online you know how much can you do
by touching your head with another
teacher we have to decide this week
maybe you can help us with suggestions
we have to make it possible for people
to get the training from South Africa or
whatever we were we are working on
finding ways to certify teachers with a
responsible mix of online and in-person
how that's going to happen is pretty
much up to this group especially the
professors okay Mentors so to teach
officially groups of over 15 outside of
your living room including online if the
over 15 people
you must be certified and you will be on
a list of certified teachers and and
what courses you're certified before if
we do it that way
we'll also be online it will be on our
website okay and we'll talk more about
that whole process there's a lot of
questions you probably have and don't
stress about it
I can't cover everything the first night
I got to do the homework but it'll be a
cool system
you will like it we want you to teach we
desperately want you to teach and you
are very valuable the people who came
here
to learn to be a teacher it took me 40
years to find you and I'm proud of each
one of you for coming and I'm gonna make
you a good teacher okay so that's the
goal
don't worry about it but I'm gonna make
you a good teacher
okay so certified teachers groups of 15
or more official a CITT you got to be
certified your name will be on a list
what if I've been teaching for 20 years
gives love and you never told me I
needed this stuff we'll have a special
deal that will work out for
grandfathering the grandfathers and
grandmothers grandfathering in as a verb
in English means special exception for
people have been teaching for a long
time already okay but still we're gonna
demand certain things that you're you
retrain yourself in certain things okay
just to make sure the quality of the
teaching is good accurate okay
accessible and relevant nice okay next
homework question the 36 formal study
courses of a CI are divided into two
broad groups
what are these groups named and what is
the primary emphasis of each of the two
groups so we have 36 courses okay
formal study courses there are some
other courses called practice modules
like special meditations like tonglen
there's a 50 page essay collected from
the classics no Geshe Michael all
classics antonin 50 pages I think and
that's a separate thing you can learn
that but the 36 main courses okay are
divided into 18 and 18 the first 18 name
on your homework which always gets
people's attention for a while is ACI
foundation courses the the 18 ACI
foundation courses okay
that's half of the formal study courses
okay and I'm gonna explain the structure
of those 18 to nine okay that's another
homework question okay but so far you
just got a name right 18 HDI foundation
courses okay by the way just you
probably most of you know the last three
16 17 and 18 are review of the first 15
okay now the second 18 courses are
Dimond way courses in the sanskrit is
about jana okay diamond way courses
right the goal okay traditionally if you
study those first 18 courses and you
work hard you can become a Buddha and
help all those stars we were talking
about in about a billion years standard
time period for our normal Buddha okay I
mean I can't even count the number its
call it a billion it's probably too
small if you study diamond way properly
accurately excessively and relevantly
you can shorten that time to this
lifetime to one lifetime okay and that's
an incredible deal you know that's a
good deal
okay but it takes a lot of training to
do the second 18 courses and and as
teachers I expect you to never teach a
person the second eighteen courses
without the first eighteen courses it's
like giving a kid a loaded gun okay they
will hurt themselves okay so I okay
and I've tried I said all this person
special tell you what you finished 12
courses I'll give you their budget Anna
they all failed I think the failure rate
for people who didn't finish the first
18 courses
is close to a hundred percent and I'm
talking big failures okay heart people
messed up people's lives messed up their
own lives okay
not cool okay so Audrianna is first
there's a there's a Sanskrit word for
those courses called Tantra okay we're
not going to use the word because it has
a bad reputation in the world even in
India okay the word Tantra has bad
reputation in the world because of
misbehavior bad behavior of teachers who
were practicing other kinds of Tundra I
was in Indonesia I won't know sorry
close Argentina and we have somebody for
Argentina where are you yeah a couple so
anyway I was asked to go to a degree and
teach in I was a cop on today's day to a
soccer team and it was cool you know and
I didn't and it was fun this is the
Monte Carlo of South America right and
it was on the beach and everything but
they were so cool we worked until two
o'clock at night together and on the in
the airport Montevideo what's it called
or the quay yeah in the airport I
thought there's a huge poster in the
bookstore its Tantra secrets sex killing
chickens you know and I was like we
can't use this for it you know so I
encourage you not to use this word okay
especially as an ASL teacher there's a
traditional name of the higher teachings
advanced teachings called Vajrayana
diamond way and I prefer to use it Tim
pointed out to me that there's a
Buddhist group calling themselves
diamond way nowadays but and there's a
group coined ourselves Kadampa also
that's fine
I'm not gonna avoid an important word
because someone's using it okay so you
know what it means it means a method to
help the whole universe in your lifetime
okay and to be honest you don't want to
go through the billion years anyway
okay okay it's doing much trouble you
got to die you got to get diarrhea I
don't know how many times you know don't
do it just plan on doing the second 18
courses they are called the diamond way
courses sometimes I call advanced
courses but I thought it was too wimpy
they're not advanced courses their
ultimate courses okay diamond way
courses and in my opinion which is
modest in my opinion because I wrote
them they are the best Audrianna courses
in history
they include every major topic of
Adriana for the first time in one course
I I was at the two Vajrayana monasteries
of Tibet and I was there the night they
started the debate ground I debated all
the students in the visor and a
monastery and kicked there but frankly
and they don't have a good of course as
we have okay I don't care okay this is
the best in the world okay so cool super
cool you can do it okay about your honor
eighteen courses so you got the answer
to the question right it's pretty simple
you're not gonna put Tantra courses and
you're not gonna call them that because
people will get the wrong idea even in
India that word is very very it for all
Indian people it's very uncomfortable to
use the word tournament because of
people who misused it okay so done so
stick to diamond ring I don't want to
see advanced courses on your homework
they're better than that okay all right
you guys okay I'm gonna go straight
through I'm older than you I have to
stand up the whole time I'm teaching
three hours in the morning I'll go like
this maybe
but if you have a pee-pee emergency you
are very welcome to just slip out rather
than taking it a ten-minute break that
turns into a half-hour break okay we
don't have much time together so if you
have a I took my old lady to the ballet
this week in Phoenix getting her out of
her nursing home getting her into the
car
get her into her realtor we were the
last people in the auditorium and they
were waiting for us
and I worked hard to get in there on
time and she sat down they started to
lower the lights and she said very
loudly I need to pee somebody already
all the ushers are angry you know
and I'm like all right you know I've cut
her in her wheelchair and they waited
for 15 minutes you know a huge
auditorium they waited for her for why
did I mention that oh I'm not gonna take
a break it's too slow okay all right two
hours straight through you okay with
that
but seriously it's not disrespectful
it's not wrong it's wrong to hurt your
body okay in Buddhism so if you if
something if you drank a couple sodas
before the class just go and don't ask
me and don't look desperate okay just
just go okay Phil's showing you the way
okay all right next topic in the very
short run my thinking when I started the
ACI courses was to share the Geshe
course with with modern people outside
of Tibet you see and I was very excited
I was finishing my gosh a degree I was
cloud three years of from finishing four
years from finishing
and I was so turned on by the Geisha
course it's so amazing it's so so cool
[Music]
by the way garish in young geisha is
short for gateways Union the Sanskrit is
kalyana Mitra and it means spiritual
friend okay so gay che is kalyana Mitra
and it's not on your homework Tori but
and but uh it means spiritual friend and
and that's what I want you to be that's
what we're trying to make you people
spiritual friend spiritual guide okay so
the gadget course is amazing and I
thought how because people were asking
me to teach Buddhism and I was like you
know blanket let's do the hot geisha
cards you know and they're like we don't
have 25 years and I said well do you
have seven years and so we tried to do
three courses six years every year so
they could have digestion time which is
highly desirable and I said okay let's
do the gushie course so I built the
eighteen foundation courses on the
gushie course and the Gashi course
started roughly a thousand years ago
okay people started getting the name
Geshe about a thousand years ago at that
time those great tsongkhapa monasteries
were still 400 years out but masters who
who studied the great classics Asian
classes and and became masters of them
were already called geishas a thousand
years ago okay in the Kadampa times
there's kadamba Geshe Dorjee sangha we
are studying his work and I guess he
told long bar we are studying his work
these are from a thousand years ago
okay so gasps she started the name the
title started a thousand years ago it
became formalized about 600 years ago
okay but that course was so interesting
and so cool that I wanted to share it
with with modern people okay
and I'm gonna brag which is very unusual
for me that is the first time women were
taught to Geshe course in history women
in Tibet were not allowed to learn to
read or write okay the name for women in
Tibetan is pume which means no penis or
came men which means lower rebirth
these are the two words in the Tibetan
language for females women and they were
not allowed to study the getti course
and we broke this tradition and we got a
lot of heat for it a lot and a lot of
criticism for it recently the people
criticized us just passed the first
woman gay but we did it ten years before
that twenty years we were a little bit
ahead right when was it two years ago
the first woman get you yeah I'm just
saying it wasn't allowed okay and so we
did it yeah so my dream was that modern
people and and people who weren't monks
were never allowed to study the Geisha
course so it's the first time people who
are not in a monastery who are not monks
or nuns and women were allowed to study
the Geisha course why I have no idea
there's 4600 texts from ancient India to
were written by women I think it may be
three I don't know okay we're breaking
this we're breaking this tradition it's
a bad tradition
okay and 99% of those traditions are
beautiful that one's bad so we're
breaking it okay and my dream was that
okay so the Geisha course is based on
five grade topics which I'm about to
tell you because they're on your
homework and you're gonna pay attention
their owner okay no you have to teach
them I'm gonna go
I've written a document in your manual
which is going to be online to save
paper and also so I can keep adding
stuff during the week I wrote a 25 page
essay about the foundation of the Geisha
course and a CIA 18 courses okay the
foundation courses so you can read that
and all of this information is there and
that that will be you'll be able to
access that tonight right am i right Tim
the manual as it's dense
yeah and parts of the manual aren't
finished you'll see yeah but the essay
about the 18 courses the 25 pages and
it's beautiful because I added color
pictures of all the llamas all the
Masters chandrakirti thermacare d guna
Papa thinks Sangha okay I did a lot of
work so five great topics are covered in
nagashi course roughly in order of
higher school because there's four great
schools and that's your last homework
question okay so five great topics
covered in four great schools of ancient
India we are not talking about what the
four schools of Tibetan Buddhism okay
we're not talking about that okay there
are four traditional schools in Tibetan
Buddhism for the last thousand years
we're not talking about that we're
talking about Buddhism for
two-and-a-half thousand years in ancient
India there were four great schools okay
and on the homework question you're
gonna have to give five names because
I'm sorry let's do the topics first five
great topics okay I'm not talking school
I'm talking Geshe topics okay and it's a
little bit different if you really want
to be cute on your homework you can
connect the five great topics to the
four great schools but I'm not even
asking for none okay I want separate
questions okay here's the five great
topics
okay should I do them in order I'd
better do it the way I did it let me see
yeah and by the way also in the I gave
you the we call it I gave you the the
schedule of the Gashi course in the
monastery the 25 years like how much
time on this subject how much time on
this okay I put it in reading okay okay
okay first of the five great topics okay
not schools okay first of the five great
topics of the keshe course yes I'm gonna
say of the Dharma okay the English name
is higher knowledge of e Dharma higher
knowledge okay the first grade topic of
the Gashi course not in order of how you
take it but in order of school is a be
Dharma higher knowledge okay I didn't
ask for it on the homework but maybe I
should have each of the five great
topics of the Geshe course has an
Associated classic great book okay so
I'm just gonna throw those names at you
it's not on your homework you can get it
off the manual okay but Stanley can
probably tell me the first one I'll be
dumb Akashi up by bus a bundle okay boss
a bundle correct spelling is in the
manual you'll see okay muscle bundles
lived 350 AD okay I'm not doing
dynasties tongue Chow Ming Qiong I'm
gonna use Western dates okay I think
we're all going to be wearing Chinese
colors before the end of my time and
talking in dynasties but right now it's
Christian days okay so call it 350 AD
the dates for these guys are there
very difficult there's no Indian history
books so forget it okay I'm just giving
you estimate okay I didn't have time to
figure it out I could probably do better
but okay
350 AD the the book is called the
treasure house of higher knowledge the
treasure house of higher knowledge okay
I'll be Tama corsa okay course you full
of north okay and and still accountants
in India are called Qataris it still
comes from kosher okay
and Stanley happens to be transiting
until 2042 is their schedule right 46 oh
we might have to speed up ah a very
important commentary but it will take 20
years to translate okay and I translated
one of the most important commentaries
first 12 years of my Geshe studies I
translated the whole commentary okay so
that's the first grade what's the topic
after the Buddha died for 700 years
just after he died some of his more
advanced students said to be our Hans
there's a debate about it collected
together collections of his topic seven
great collections of his teachings and
they called those literature higher
knowledge okay so that was collected
together by students after the Buddha
and they kind of messed up some
important points okay but 90% of it is
extremely important as a foundation of
all Buddhism
okay so abhidharma is important it does
not contain the highest teachings on
emptiness okay and for 700 years after
the Buddha this is what was thought
okay that's what reached Srilanka
Thailand Burma okay
this tradition okay all right what's the
subject matter I describe it this way
Oh anyway just about every major idea
that the Buddha thought okay it's like
an encyclopedia and you're constantly
referring back to it for example the
four steps of DC I come from there the
the four laws of karma come from there
the four flowers come from there the
four steps of confession come from there
it's an amazing resource okay it's an
encyclopedia okay
second grade topic is called the Nile
vowed morality promising through a
commitment to keep to a moral code an
ethical code okay and there are eight
great divisions and you will study it
during the ACR courses okay
vinaya okay the nya comes from a root
that means to tame a wild horse okay so
that's what we're doing Allison's
translating some coppers greatest work
on it summary okay the great book here
for studying commitments it's called the
Vinaya Sutra okay and we can write after
that you should say it's not a Sutra
okay Sutra technically means a teaching
given directly by the Buddha and but it
can also mean a short book or a short
classic some of them are 12,000 pages
but like the yoga Sutra
okay 210 verses that's all it's about 12
pages or something okay so the the
Vinaya Sutra is the book we use to study
vinaya in the monastery but it's not a
sutra it's just a short book okay you
can call it a short book on valid
morality okay and the author's name is
guna
gee you and a PRA BHA and it's in your
reading it's in your manual don't stress
about writing things I'm not using
visuals because you it's in your manual
okay I don't want you to waste your time
looking at a screen okay I want you to
listen to oral in the niche okay good no
papa
about 550 ad okay pretty late 550 ad
okay third grade topic in Sanskrit is
Pomona say Pomona if you want to be
really good role the end bag hermano I
would like a cup of tea if you'd run in
mind okay a lot of Sanskrit is said with
a tongue hermana okay pramana means
valid perception correct position I have
changed the name of the third topic to
clear thinking clear thinking and I'm
very happy okay
it took me twenty seven years but I'm
happy with it I never did like Buddhist
perception in a mystical logical theory
okay
what it is is clear thinking okay and
you have to be trained in how to think
clearly and it's an incredibly valuable
tool for all Buddhist okay so it's
called Pomona clear thinking okay how to
think clearly what are the rules for
thinking clearly and then by the way
lots of information about how we
perceive things for example the crucial
discussion of DCI levels some chi chi
dark chi chi dark okay general and
characteristics we're gone okay quality
and characteristic okay very deep this
topic is called in buddhism the key to
emptiness it's extremely important okay
it's not some boring thing I lost half
my students when I taught ACI 13
thirteen is a bad luck number in the
West I don't what's a bad luck number in
China ba Baba is good right for ya
anyway 13 is really bad luck in in
Western countries because the Jesus is
13th student killed helped him get
killed so 13 is a bad number
they don't have 13th floor on most
buildings in America why did I say that
Oh course 13 which was logic I lost half
my students that that that year okay and
I'm gonna teach you the flow by the way
why did I teach one course after another
and you should know that by the time we
finished this week okay you're gonna
know the names of the 18 courses you're
gonna be able to tell me the main ideas
in the 18 courses and you're gonna Tempe
temp you're gonna tell me which even get
a lot didn't know why did he teach this
one next okay but I I would he call it
revision I I went back and figured out a
flow okay uh all right the school here
by the way is the suit wrist school in
Sanskrit you don't need to know in the
sense man sutra school followers of
sutra guess what okay mr. know-it-all
yeah don't look around why is it called
the sutra school why did they choose the
name citrus for themselves so the first
school is called like I be dumb okay or
vinaya I'm by the way vinaya is just
part of the hobby Dharma school okay
same school okay what's citrus
good
yeah they say to the abhidhamma guys
you're just reading stuff that was put
together by the students we want to read
the hinging in the gene gun we want to
go to the sutras we want to put his own
word okay so the second school you can
call them logic school or you can call
them sutras
let's go because they say we only want
Sutra we only want what the Buddha
actually said okay and then they ended
up being very interested in how do you
think clearly because that's a tool that
every Buddhist needs why the important
stuff for getting out of suffering are
things you cannot see with your eyes and
ears you must develop your mental
capacity you must develop your clear
thinking to see things that cannot be
seen by it by the eyes and the ears you
must learn to develop this tool pramana
okay you must learn to develop your mind
to see things that you can't see with
your eyes sometimes you can call it
third eye okay so the third eye is not
some weird diamond way thing it's the
ability to see things that cannot like
emptiness they cannot be seen with your
eyes okay you develop this muscle here
okay all right next topic - a topic how
many guess you topics fine good how many
schools four but five if you split the
four school into two okay but we didn't
get there yet
okay okay fourth major topic of the
Geshe course we're kind of going up
schools is it's called the perfection of
wisdom it's called the perfection of
wisdom
okay progeny parameter in Chinese
bora-bora middle
okay progeny say Pratt senior para meet
that and actually Russian is the closest
modern language I'm aware of to Sanskrit
it's it's very precise close to Russia
so there you would say senior right for
for I know yeah I know yes neo
it's much closer to the Sanskrit and and
in general Russian pronunciation is is
much closer to the Sanskrit it's cool so
anyway now perfection of wisdom has at
least three major meanings that
contradict each other so you better know
which perfection of wisdom you're
talking about okay when you talk about
the gadget topic the fourth Geshe topic
which is named perfection the wisdom
into the in tibetan Parchin puchen just
short name Parchin okay it's the study
of the lower middle way school
perfection the wisdom in the gadget
course only means the study of the lower
half of the middle waist called high
school okay it's only done why because
those early middle way works by baba
vivica asanga these present every major
topic of Mahayana every major topic of
the higher way okay
so super cool all right it's it's when
you reach president parameter in the
monastery the fourth major topic that
you start the greater way Mahayana okay
don't call my honor to your students
learn to use your language Russian
Spanish whatever don't drown your
students understand credit okay don't
force them to learn the same thing with
an older name you're just putting
obstacles in their way
okay so perfection of wisdom in the
monastery course in the Geshe course it
just means the study of the lower half
of the middle way okay-y vast
encyclopedia of all greats ideas of
Mahayana except for the perfect
explanation of emptiness okay so it's
pretty cool and frankly it's half of the
getti course it's twelve years of the
Gaussian course okay it must be
important okay I forgot to give you the
important book for the pramana
clear-thinking schools okay it's by
Dharma Quixote and don't mix up your
cuties okay you know I went on wiki to
see the dates for Dom acuity that they
thought and the picture of the Lama
under Dom acuity in Wikipedia is
chandrakirti and it says that under the
picture in Tibetan so I wrote all my
friends who do that kind of stuff I said
can you fix it they stole the picture
from me which is okay I got it in Russia
but and it has the name under it and
they put it under the wrong kitties so
don't get your gear cuties mixed up okay
Darmok NT is the great logician okay and
we study his book called our commentary
on valid perception or clear thinking
okay in that case what's valid
perception or clear thinking mean it's
the work of his teacher digna
that's why it's a commentary okay but
I'm not telling you that
just put Dharma candy okay by the way
it's a tradition in Buddhism never to
speak of your teacher your personal lama
with that we call their naked name Jumba
Ming Jimbo so we're not really supposed
to say Dharma charity and in ACI courses
we try to use the word master
Chinese people have a very good custom
they always say Oh Michael laughs gushy
gushy Michael mouths shut
they always say louder I mean if you
taught them how to change a tire on a
car they'll call you Russia it's very
polite and it's a tradition in Buddhism
we say master Dharma Cathy and I prefer
that you do that you don't have to be a
Buddhist to study a CI and you don't
have to be a Buddhist to teach a CI but
you should be respectful of the lineage
you call it master Dharma kitty okay
dates from master Dharma Quixote 650 ad
now who wrote the big book for fourth
topping well actually is Maitreya and
then his secretary got credit for it a
Sangha okay and what's the so the book
is by Maitreya slash a Sangha you can
enter it that way if you want
half-brother of us abandon 350 AD okay
same mother and what's the book called
either jewel of realizations the jewel
of realizations in Sanskrit up he's Sam
Mayer Allen Carter a besom okay but you
don't need to know that okay just put
jewel of realizations very very
important for example Dana Suginami obey
King is in Anyang shooting a tangent
dodging Newton on Blue Beetle etapa J we
have to memorize most of these books in
the monastery these five great books
that's the whole source for two things
lions Stanton and that and thousands of
books on the on the twelve links is to
two lines of Sanskrit okay it's a hot
book okay
twelve years of the keshe course okay
fifth topic I know you're getting tired
you're gonna be worse in a couple of
days so just enjoy fifth topic come on
middle way okay
oh by the way the other two meanings are
perfection of wisdom which is not what
it means in the Getty course is the
sixth perfection of a bodhisattva the
sixth activity of a bodhisattva the
sixth topic of training for all body
suffers is wisdom progeny parameter okay
the other meaning of personal parameter
is a huge group of sutras where the
Buddha taught emptiness but sometimes
two very long stories like the eight
thousand verses or the twenty thousand
verses or the twenty five thousand
verses or the hundred thousand verses
okay it's a huge section in the
scriptures called perfection with them
so don't get confused okay as I get it
topic it means the lower half of the
middle way which is big deal not dummies
okay okay here's the important Homer
question nah I'll tell you later okay
yeah I got your attention though all
right so this fourth topic I'm sorry the
fifth topic is middle way middle way
also refers to the fourth topic right
there the lower half of the middle way
so don't forget when you're lifting
Geshe topics or you go to the monastery
and they ask you what do you guys
studying nowadays Houston right names
they are nicknames
there are misnomers okay middle way
means the study of the higher half of
the middle way school okay it's the
study of the higher half of the middle
way school the big big big book which is
not the main book study is Nagar genus
wisdom it's just called wisdom ok buying
the Gartner 280 does that dates charkham
strike a bell
ringing a bell yes when Buddhism came
back to what it was 700 years after 700
years of Stanley chance abhidhamma
okay then their Guardian that came back
and said hey you guys are missing
emptiness man you don't got it right you
know so he came we call him his nickname
is second Buddha on this planet second
Buddha to walk on this planet okay
200 AD he wrote a book which is
sometimes just called it's called wisdom
but sometimes it's called just called
the middle way okay so the most famous
commentary online is called entering the
middle way meaning the gardener's book
okay it doesn't mean the middle way as
it as a school and that's by master Chun
master chandrakirti okay around
I think it's 6:15 any check I put what I
wrote here
I can't find it but yeah 650 okay yeah
650 mmm you guys with me okay can I just
keep going yeah yeah yeah because the
nickname of the book wisdom is its
middle way okay
so entering the middle way is actually
means learning to read Nakajima okay
and so it doesn't mean entering middle
way philosophy for example although by
although we are okay okay good question
so those are the five great books we
memorize most of them in the monastery
over the course of the gushy gushy
course okay I did all of the abuse on
Cara I did the first four chapters of
the double crochet which was it I almost
said and and you know I've done
pieces of the other ones okay but you
need that to walk you shouldn't walk on
the debate ground if you don't have them
in your head okay all right now I'm
gonna present them by school so now we
go to another homework question the four
schools and it's actually the last
homework question and I'm actually
timing this class not so bad except I
didn't get to your ACI course but that's
okay I promised him I wouldn't do this
but I'm doing it okay you might have to
do half the homework to mine
math to do homeworks in house but anyway
okay the four schools the four great
schools of ancient India okay
they overlap a little bit we'll see
first great school called detail list
detail list okay
this means a member of a group in
English you know like republicanism
anyway
dudas for example okay yeah so detail
list anybody okay human anybody want to
tell me why who's not the human
dictionary hustle why are they called
detail list now I mean it's a good guess
but there's a book called yeah there's a
book called the detailed explanation
which is what they follow that's their
main abhidharma book that's their book
okay yeah detail last means by pashenka
but part of the title of the book is by
by Prussia
okay so deep a list just means their
people the first school of the four
great schools of India is called people
who like to read the book the detailed
explanation okay and it's one of the
books of all time okay by básico
okay by parsekar all right you don't
need to know the spelling it's in urine
by the way it's so nice to see so many
people jet lag and I don't have because
all year it's the opposite second grade
school oh by the way Abby Dharma of now
Gary topic in the four schools what's in
the first school which cares your topic
to great avi Dharma and vanaya
are in the first school so don't get
confused between schools
and topics I'm trying to confuse you but
show me you're smarter than that five
topics for schools they over they go
like this okay so first topic higher
knowledge second topic dog morality are
both part of the first school the lowest
school by the way I'm going up by Bosch
chica bye-bye detail list abhidharma and
denial okay
I prefer you don't use foreign words in
your class you know you use them because
you're used to them you know conking you
know but but just try to remember the
the first class you walked into I
remember the first class I walked into
and people were like well the vibe are
chica approach to the darkness not
exactly what was born with symbolism
work on the question of ally of is
nursing and I'm like and for them it's
very easy they they they've been in it
for ten years but don't forget your
students are not don't confuse them with
a lot of sounds good
don't don't make them I'll be Dharma
sounds come to offer you because you
heard it from ten years okay so don't do
that to them call it higher knowledge
okay first school detailer school second
school we talked about it suit wrists
suit wrists okay they follow the sutras
we don't want those huge summaries done
by human beings after the Buddha died we
want the right suitor who want the
diamond cut we want the real suit dress
we want what he said okay citrus okay
you can calm logic school sometimes we
call them logic school
now we're gonna call them clear thinking
school
okay clear think he's go okay that's
their main thing topic number three okay
topic number three now with the first
two schools and with the first three
topics we have finished the branch
called the lower way the lower way okay
now you should know something about
lower way in Tibetan to take men men
means lower women are called game men
same word lower beings okay
I hope they changed the language they
probably could if they really wanted to
you know that's something the friends
were doing they'd have the courage to
say let's change this word it's not nice
so anyway those are lower way literally
Hina Hina Jana Jana Jana Hinayana okay
Hina means inferior lower okay Hinayana
okay now you visit Sri Lanka you visit
Thailand you visit Burma do not call it
Hinayana you might go to jail in their
country it's Tara Baba the true way tera
vaada okay so get if you want to be
polite in a Buddhist group from one of
those countries don't use the word
Hinayana it's like lower berth it's like
calling a woman or lower berth it's not
polite okay it's kind of not very sweet
okay but in our scriptures it's called
lower way okay it's the same word lower
okay so the first two schools are him
they honor and how many topics are
Hinayana three or tera vaada if you're
sitting with people from Sri Lanka and
Burma all right
[Music]
third school minam let's go okay
minam let's go where is it in the five
Gashi topics $50 question don't get I am
mentioned money to people get excited
wah $25 to get the question okay anyway
you're both wrong I save my money I mean
you're both not exactly precise okay now
when does I guess I study the mind only
school okay exactly okay course number
15 what the Buddha really meant okay
what the Buddha really meant okay we
studied it for ye months in a certain
city in China yeah
I'm about refer to that but hang with me
so the main place in the geisha course
thank you when you study mind only is
when you study a cook a Sutra called
what the Buddha what I really meant what
I really meant okay and as the guys in
the CS pure gold program can tell you
Buddha taught three great periods in his
life forget the ACI course what I'm
going to do tomorrow Buddha taught three
great courses in his life three great
periods of his teaching first one is I
call it the list period he made list
hey there's four truths there's twelve
links there's eight fold our path
there's a four plus that's a confession
there's a force test to come there's a
four letter camera there's a six you
know it's like pow okay it's the list
period of his life the first teaching
for example he ever taught
what's the for truth okay so he's just
making this he was ten non-virtuous
here's the organizing stuff for people
okay and then in the middle part of his
life he got up on a mountain vultures
peak and he said by the way always list
I gave you
the stuff in those lists it don't exist
it's not real every list I gave you
every piece of every list was not real
huh it's like a joke you know I fooled
you guys for 20 years you know so guess
what happened people freaked out people
you know and people came to him part of
Martha's some woodcutter I buddy stopped
and he said listen you spent the whole
first part of your teaching career
giving us lists and we believe they only
practiced them then we got to the second
party or a teaching career
like diamond mountain or something
instead of New York and then you said by
the way that list I gave you in New York
is all PBS not a bit exist you know and
we're we're like confused mr. Buddha
like what's the real one which one was
real what are two famous citrus from the
second period the second turning of the
wheel
yeah the diamond cutters to turn the
hearts it dressed okay
like nothing exists nothing's real okay
so naturally some people are gonna come
and say what the whoa what are you
talking about you know everything's not
real and he said look you didn't get it
you know let me explain it a different
way and he taught three characteristics
of da mind on his car and then he
thought the mind on this car okay
which the middle way school understood
to be middle a school even in the third
part of his life and that started an
argument that lasts until now okay when
Buddha by the way the third turning of
the wheel is called clarifications the
second turning rules called emptiness
the first turn the wheel is called lists
okay turning of the wheel means teaching
period but why turning meal why is that
the symbol of Buddhism yeah you pat I'm
turning the wheel right now and then
you're gonna turn the wheel when you get
certified as a DCI teacher or you're
gonna turn the wheel on the airplane
unofficially as a living room teaching
okay so three the third Korean it's very
interesting because the mind only guy
said oh let's start a school called my
know me and the middleweight guy said
come on he's just talked about the same
thing you talked about before okay
got it anyway you don't get to study
that argument until after you finish
higher middle way it's considered part
of higher middle way it's considered in
the Geshe course it's considered part of
higher middle way but as Steven pointed
out correctly it comes up very
importantly
in the teachings on karma and it came up
in the abbe Salman car right very
important subjects about the mind only
school so you can say the mine only
school touches on the other schools in
different places but the main foundation
of the mind on the school is the middle
way school okay they take off from their
argument with the middle let's go okay
third school which topic in the
monastery in the Geshe course we're good
know of the fire yeah we're gonna throw
it in the highest Midway because that's
where you study tonguing okay that's
where he studied ringing okay we don't
have a separate course in middle in mind
only in the monastery okay all right hmm
for school middle way okay that middle
way is not the same as the middle way
which is a topic of the Geshe course
okay as a school middle way is the 4th
in high school as agasshi topic it's the
fifth topic it's not the same thing okay
why
yeah as a school middle-way
is number four and it includes two parts
and the lower part is the fourth Geshe
topic which is not commonly confusing
yeah which is also the name and the
guardians book they started the whole
problem okay so as a school middle way
is the fourth school in the highest as a
topic it's the fifth topic as a school
it has two little schools in it two
groups as a topic it's always the higher
of those two groups got it
no higher okay all right now
since it's on your homework and we're
almost done
there's two schools in the in the middle
two groups okay III asked you for the
rest of your life to call them the
groups of the middle way school okay
first one is called in English
independent group the independent group
okay the independent group they're
called independent okay
and they wrote the books for the
geschichte topic number four which is
not calm in a way which is called
perfect oh okay I'm sorry I'm just
trying to if you show up in the
monastery and say you're studying middle
way and you talk about the lower middle
way you're in trouble okay all right now
what we learned in our translation
classes in Sedona which you're always
welcome to come to there's a tuition fee
to pay for the air conditioning and
you're always welcome to sign up and we
cover the classics we translated three
thousand pages in the last two years
no one has ever done that okay it's an
awesome course you should you're welcome
to come and sit in or
you have to pay the fee I'm sorry and in
that in that course we learned a cool
reason why the lower school is called
independent okay ready
it's cool it's super sexy to me Buddha
said things don't grow from themselves
things don't grow from other things
things don't grow from both and things
don't grow from nothing
that's very famous okay a big guy in the
lower middle way school said Buddha left
a word out he should have said things
they'll go from themselves number two
and things they'll go from something
else from their own side ultimately he
should have said that because normally
things do grow from other things trees
grow from seeds stomachaches girl from
Charles you know so this lower middle
way guy said you should have said he
should have said ultimately they don't
go from other things when you say don't
go from other things you confuse
everybody because they do go from other
things you should just say they don't go
from other things ultimately then
everybody will understand what you're
talking about because when you say
things don't go from other things well
what about trees okay got it
now one hundred dollars why should that
opinion except forward you get ten
dollars why should that opinion because
independent yeah they think the word has
its own power independent power because
if someone's gonna miss understand
doesn't grow from something else
they're also gonna misunderstand
ultimately because both words are empty
they don't have power from their own
side the power word comes from you you
make a movie that your last movie you
saw Netflix is coming from you
that's why they don't make money just
kidding
got it if you think it's gonna be easier
for someone if you say the word
ultimately then you must think that word
has more power than the other word but
words don't have any power the power in
words comes from you
got it you're probably the only people
in the world who understand why that
school is named going to this know
what's the name of the higher Midway
school we're almost done yeah
consequence consequence
okay consequence present Giga why called
consequence so word comes out to me and
says gala I have an idea I said what all
fruits are orange I saw orange tell me
how to Orange
somebody had a tangerine I got this idea
all fruits are orange okay ready then I
say oh really look at this banana
I guess it's orange okay so the highest
middle high school is called what
they're called consequence referring to
the absurd consequences of the other guy
statements the crazy implications of the
other parties ideas okay got it
if you think I should have used the word
ultimate then I also should have said
fish
right defective has the real meaning it
always refers to things that go like
this right from its own sign right okay
you could never call fishing looking for
girls right because it has its own
meaning got it okay you're getting the
deep explanations okay the highest
middle a school is called consequence or
resolved you see because if you believe
a wrong idea about emptiness the result
is you're gonna say stupid things like
all fruits are orange okay got it
and the way we fight those people is we
say we don't say look word all fruits
are not orange there's other in fruits
there's red apples there's yellow
bananas that's not that chill system of
the highest mentally the chill system of
the highest middle way is to show to put
a banana and a stick in his face and say
you want this orange fruit word you know
you don't say I disagree you don't say
not off with our orange you don't say
this this fruit is yellow you say Oh
word here's another orange flip for you
okay that's called ridiculous
consequence of his own position the
highest middle weight school is called
that no we're out of time
am i right we got three minutes last
question on your homework I know I said
that already I was just trying to keep
your attention last question honest just
like what I really meant
that's curse on your homework how do we
divide the four ancient schools into two
groups
on what basis do we say Hinayana and
Mahayana for example you can say
motivation okay
the the lower two schools are supposedly
not interested in saving the universe
they only the three goals I out laid out
for sei right number one make people
happy number two change the model of the
world number three go to serious change
the universe okay they don't believe in
number three they actually don't believe
in number two months okay they just want
to be happy okay
that's the traditional way to explain
the difference between mahayana and
hinayana but if you read Darby Dharma
kosha they discuss body surface and they
discuss saving the world and being
enlightened oh I'm gonna kiss you but
you got their beard perfect yeah it's
perfect yeah that's the second answer to
the question the question says I want
two answers number one lower school
higher school lower school doesn't help
buddy stop us they don't want to save
the universe higher schools mind only in
middle way they want to save the
universe
I'll be Dharma I'm sorry sue tristin
Detailers they don't want to save the
universe but they do and it's in their
books duh but that's a traditional
answer okay now if you want to go deeper
which is ACI teachers I'm sure talk
about it in terms of the six flavors of
emptiness the way divided the schools
the way divided the four schools the way
divided Hinayana and Mahayana is all
based on how good is their emptiness
explanation okay how good is it all
right let's do it you won't be able to
stay late later because you'll be too
tired
okay you wanna let's do it quick okay
we're gonna talk about the six flavors
the emptiness that are the true basis of
the differences between the schools
because you gotta understand the
differences between schools to
understand the structure of the Geshe
course which you have to understand if
you're gonna understand the structure of
the HDI foundation courses got it
okay I'm trying to make you a real NCI
teacher who understands what the hell is
a CI okay you gotta know the schools you
gotta know the the topics okay ready
and you gotta know the six layers the
emptiness to know why the first two
schools are lower and the second two
schools are higher way
Mahayana Hinayana got it someone give me
the first flavor emptiness quick quick
we did it a like ten times in your city
yeah things art by the way every time
you teach the six flavors the emptiness
start out the sentence with the same
words things are empty of or things
don't have okay and then the blank fill
in the blank for the first flavor
emptiness is things don't have lasting
forever
okay your husband's not gonna be yelling
at you forever he's gotta sleep he's
gotta eat okay
take refuge which is real refuge in the
understanding that he has to change
he cannot yell all night most of the
night yes he's got to take a break okay
and that's the lowest form of emptiness
your husband who is yelling at you by
the way right now we're being relevant
to real life your husband can't yell
forever take refuge in emptiness first
play for emptiness nothing lasts forever
what's the famous example I always give
in when I discuss it Abraham Lincoln the
most compassionate president in American
history had to kill more people than any
American president well that's okay but
and when he had his big meeting with the
generals he said the only good thing
about this war is it won't last forever
okay so that's a lololo refuge it don't
work too good
okay I'll put up on my husband because
uh you go to bed soon yeah
okay it's not a very effective emptiness
you know it'd be nice if you could just
stop him from ever yelling but if you
don't know that higher emptiness take
refuge in the Lord emptiness which is
real Buddhist refuge you know I'm gonna
wait I'm not gonna say anything he can
keep yelling he's got to take a break
sooner or later you know he's gotta go
to pee pee like you guys okay Louis for
man thenis what school yeah Louis school
law school detail is good second kind of
emptiness yeah okay
there's okay second kind of emptiness
you cannot control things in this life
forget it okay that'll come a day when
you can't raise your arm okay don't tell
me you can control your husband or your
finances or your country okay you can't
control your finger okay in the end in
the hospital someone will have to hand
you the water trust me I've been there
so many times in this life okay
someone will have you will be able to
you don't have control you can't control
anything take refuge in this lower
emptiness where are you in the kitchen
look okay he's gonna yell Infineon you
know I tried I talked to him I I died I
did everything he's still yelling I
can't get I can't control everything
okay just relax okay
is it a solution no does it help yes
that's lower school
that's a definition of lower score is it
a solution no doesn't make you feel
better
yeah which cool is it yeah you're right
second school mostly okay second school
mostly you gotta kind of say mostly okay
third flavor emptiness for zero dollars
yeah good yeah tiny that I need you be
kill kill shipping tiny to be juicier
yeah but I keep saying YouTube it don't
bother
kill kill ship it yukkuri in bak monkey
seneca do a bit dog things are empty of
being called what they're called because
that's what they have to be called
things are empty of their names okay
how Shakespeare say it I'm sorry it
doesn't really matter you can mix three
and four if you want okay Lucas right
I'll go your way it's probably my way we
do it with our elbow right mind only
school right here's a scene you yelled
at your kids a week ago a week went by
the seed matured then you walked into
the kitchen and the seed opened into you
and your husband one seed splits into
subject and object don't tell me your
husband's a bad man you are a bad person
you created the Yeller and the yelly you
created the Yeller and the person
getting yelled at don't blame don't
blame him
you created him who brought you in the
kitchen who brought him in the kitchen
when he talked why are you whining why
are you getting angry if you don't like
it stop yelling at your kids don't plant
the tree if you don't like the branches
got it
what school are you sure this is not a
solution to the problems of the universe
stop making bad seed that split into
husband and wife sounds pretty good to
me yeah good okay but when you explain
I'm not gonna go there I will go there I
don't care if you don't sneem
the mine only school says the husband
side of that equation is a video playing
inside of your mind he don't exist
outside of your mind so you shouldn't
get mad at him he's a video that you
planted in your own mind okay got it
I had a profound question for $100 that
someone asked me about this hmm
and my aloneness is worth $25 yeah when
I kiss my husband am i kissing myself it
was a deep philosophical question okay
you got it
who's keeping John Allison can you keep
track of money I'll get he gets 75 Peter
gets 23 okay not euros okay okay got it
it's not a bad idea unless you say it's
all happening inside your head which
they do say and that's why it's a lower
emptiness got it okay next one is names
I've rose by any other name would smell
the same okay for worldview number four
emptiness number four okay it doesn't
matter because they're both mine only I
reserve the right to confuse them okay
they're both mine only okay and that is
it's not true that things are called
what they're called self-existent lis
okay which has big implications okay
like politicians are always some
disaster happens and they call it a
different name they put a spin on it you
know it's so good the economy went down
this month because it can go up next
month more you know and you're like okay
you can use names for anything okay you
can call her official rose it's okay
names don't belong to what they're used
for which also implies you have the
freedom to call the problem with the
husband
the opportunity for growth okay
and it's true and it helps right when
your husband's healing yeah you can say
gee now we're stuck the economy is so
much lower think how much higher we can
get you know if we start talking to each
other civilly we've made progress from
yesterday got it okay you can make
opportunities out of problems that's the
fourth worldview according to some
schools of a CI number five you don't
have a thing you don't have a laptop or
microphone until you have an accurate
perception of it okay it's not there
everything needs 5050 50 percent there
has to be a square here and some metal
50% geshe-la has to be not drunk not
crazy and between those two things we
get a laptop
okay got it 50 percent comes from the
object 50 percent comes from is
something which is a big difference from
the lower schools that say everything
comes from the object sign the pen comes
from the objects are 100% so this
worldview number fire it's a pretty big
jump you see half of that pen comes from
me got it half of that parents coming
from me hard it's coming this way
half of it's coming from me we meet in
the middle that's reality
got it lonely man another one get
shocked on mine but you do on keep to
Miami to look to linking money to pay
for okay
that's the emptiness no new Mellon oh I
wanna shut remember not simply
established with the help of an
unaffected unrung uncrazy state of mind
the object to moment we do this it to be
torah is appearing from its own side but
not on 100
ten on its own power okay
emptiness Laura middle-way got it y'all
right did I lose you
yeah I don't care okay highest score
highest highest if you don't want your
husband to yell in the kitchen stop
yelling at your kids okay it's all
coming from that it is empty of coming
from anything else that's highest MP
nuts got it
it is empty of coming from anybody else
except yelling at your kids and that's
the highest viewpoint okay now that's
the real guessing method of dividing the
four schools got it it's not by book
it's not by author it's not by
historical period hysterical period and
it's not by what they think about saving
the whole world or not okay it's by how
sophisticated is their presentation that
emptiness got it
so that's your last homework question
yes yeah lower middle way yeah which in
the Geshe topics has a nickname yeah
perfection of wisdom come on yeah did I
confuse you guys all right
is all for car
yeah
[Music]
somewhere in the history of my teaching
career no doubt I'd said that but I'm
not completely if you don't mind
yeah it is it's yeah yeah that's a good
question
I have an answer for you hmm
I will just what a project I put a
focuses on which is dependent
origination how's that okay and listener
would focus on the fortress how's that
see you then
the chandrakirti says the to lead to the
he bounced down to the lower or huts
because they are the true source of
Buddhist and he goes down to he bounced
down to listeners because the listener
arts because they have gained their
realization based on the fortress and he
passed down to protect Buddha our Hut's
because they are based on realizations
on the twelve links of dependent
origination but that's the main
difference
I'll adjust that but probably that says
that somewhere the other thing okay so
you're only gonna get the homework
Jaqueline they only get the teacher
training homework and they don't get the
ACI and I'll I'll try to teach what I'm
supposed to teach tomorrow but now you
have an appreciation of the of the -
ofcourse and of ACI you understand ACI
what we have to do next is go through
the 18 courses of the Foundation series
and not the diamond race series and and
we have to look at what school and and
what flavor emptiness and what gets you
talking okay that's what I want you once
you know
things you can be a real easy a teacher
you can you understand the whole
structure of of the HDI courses cool
cool man okay
hey John cool okay all right
Connie miss Connie
by the way I don't want a CI to be a
Buddhist sect of any kind but I think
the prayers are cool the pre Buddhist
prayers are cool because it's a prayer
for the final goal of Asia we want to
take the starting XI and
and by the Sun Legendre Mayday
[Music]
don't signature come here
the army the Sun yes
Santosh Santosh and Taj cool by Sunday
you have to know those two Perth in the
original pronunciation by tomorrow you
gotta be able to get your fingers like
that no you see you forgot how hard it
was the first time okay thank you thank
you for being here thank you for having
the courage to take the ACI teacher
training we will make you good teachers
you you you stay you finish you'll be a
kick-ass teacher okay
well that's our commitment okay and and
you can help more people than any other
way in your life okay
there's no way to help other people more
than this wisdom okay and that's the
greatest thing you've done in your life
I can tell you from 66 it's the best
thing I ever did
okay you too alright thank you
[Applause]